Yao Yao

Tenure-track Associate Professor

School of Intelligence Science and Technology, Nanjing University

Email: yaoyao@nju.edu.cn Phone: (+86)13680096330

Homepage: https://yoyo000.github.io

ABOUT

I am a tenure-track associate professor at School of Intelligence Science and Technology, Nanjing University, where I establish and direct the 3D Vision Lab (NJU-3DV). Previously, I was a senior researcher at Apple, and a founding member of the startup company Altizure (acquired by Apple in 2020). I received my PhD degree from CSE, HKUST in 2019, supervised by Prof. Long Quan; and my bachelor degree from ECE, NJU in 2015, advised by Prof. Xun Cao.

My research interests lie in the intersection of computer vision and computer graphics, with a focus on **3D** reconstruction, differentiable rendering, and **3D** content creation. My representative works include the MVSNet series of works for multi-view reconstruction, the large-scale BlendedMVS dataset for geometry-related learning tasks, and the NeILF series of works for physically-based differentiable rendering. I have won the ICPR 2020 Best Student Paper Award (5 over 3250 submissions), and am a recipient of the Excellent Young Scholars Fund (Overseas) from NSFC.

Google scholar: https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=MGxaDVEAAAAJ

WORK EXPERIENCES

Associate Professor

June 2023 - now

Nanjing University

- Founder and Director of Nanjing University 3D Vision Lab (NJU-3DV).
- Research focuses: 3D Reconstruction, differentiable rendering, 3D content creation.

Senior Researcher

April 2020 - May 2023

Apple Inc.

- Lead researches on differentiable rendering and 3D content creation.
- Develop core algorithms for 3D computer vision.

Founding Member

July 2015 - April 2020

Altizure.com (HKUST startup, acquired by Apple)

- Lead researches and prototype products related to 3D computer vision.
- Develop an accurate and robust MVS pipeline for large-scale 3D reconstruction.

EDUCATION

The Hong Kong University of Science and Technology

Sep. 2015 - Dec. 2019

PhD in Computer Science and Engineering

Thesis: Learning Large-Scale Multi-View Stereopsis

Supervisor: Prof. Long Quan

Nanjing University

Sep. 2011 - July 2015

BSc in Electronic Information Science and Technology Undergraduate Thesis: Research on Multi-view Stereo

Advisor: Prof. Xun Cao

- *Corresponding author
- 1. Jingyang Zhang, Shiwei Li, Yuanxun Lu, Tian Fang, David McKinnon, Yanghai Tsin, Long Quan, Yao Yao*. JointNet: Extending Text-to-Image Diffusion for Dense Distribution Modeling. arXiv preprint 2023.
- 2. Jingyang Zhang, Yao Yao*, Shiwei Li, Jingbo Liu, Tian Fang, David McKinnon, Yanghai Tsin, Long Quan. NeILF++: Inter-Reflectable Light Fields for Geometry and Material Estimation. ICCV 2023.
- 3. Jingyang Zhang, Shiwei Li, Zixin Luo, Tian Fang, **Yao Yao***. Vis-MVSNet: Visibility-aware Multiview Stereo Network. **IJCV** 2022.
- 4. Yao Yao, Jingyang Zhang, Jingbo Liu, Yihang Qu, Tian Fang, David McKinnon, Yanghai Tsin, Long Quan. NeILF: Neural Incident Light Field for Physically-based Material Estimation. ECCV 2022.
- 5. Jingyang Zhang, **Yao Yao***, Shiwei Li, Tian Fang, David McKinnon, Yanghai Tsin, Long Quan. Critical Regularizations for Neural Surface Reconstruction in the Wild. **CVPR** 2022.
- 6. Jingyang Zhang, **Yao Yao***, Long Quan. Learning Signed Distance Field for Multi-view Surface Reconstruction. **ICCV** 2021. (Oral)
- 7. Jingyang Zhang, **Yao Yao***, Shiwei Li, Zixin Luo, Tian Fang. Visibility-aware Multi-view Stereo Network. **BMVC** 2020. (Oral)
- 8. Jingyang Zhang, **Yao Yao***, Zixin Luo, Shiwei Li, Tianwei Shen, Tian Fang, Long Quan. Learning Stereo Matchability in Disparity Regression Networks. **ICPR** 2020. (**Best Student Paper Award**)
- 9. Yao Yao, Zixin Luo, Shiwei Li, Jingyang Zhang, Yufan Ren, Lei Zhou, Tian Fang, Long Quan. BlendedMVS: A Large-scale Dataset for Generalized Multi-view Stereo Networks. CVPR 2020. (>200 citations)
- 10. **Yao Yao**, Zixin Luo, Shiwei Li, Tianwei Shen, Tian Fang, Long Quan. Recurrent MVSNet for High-resolution Multi-view Stereo Depth Inference. **CVPR** 2019. (>400 citations)
- 11. **Yao Yao**, Zixin Luo, Shiwei Li, Tian Fang, Long Quan. MVSNet: Depth Inference for Unstructured Multi-view Stereo. **ECCV** 2018. (Oral, >800 citations)
- 12. **Yao Yao**, Shiwei Li, Siyu Zhu, Hanyu Deng, Tian Fang, Long Quan. Relative Camera Refinement for Accurate Dense Reconstruction. **3DV** 2017.
- 13. **Yao Yao**, Hao Zhu, Yongming Nie, Xiaoli Ji, Xun Cao. Revised depth map estimation for multi-view stereo. **IC3D** 2014.
- 14. Yifei Zeng, Yuanxun Lu, Xinya Ji, **Yao Yao**, Hao Zhu, Xun Cao. AvatarBooth: High-Quality and Customizable 3D Human Avatar Generation. **arXiv** preprint 2023.
- 15. Yiyu Zhuang, Qi Zhang, Ying Feng, Hao Zhu, **Yao Yao**, Xiaoyu Li, Yan-Pei Cao, Ying Shan, Xun Cao. Anti-Aliased Neural Implicit Surfaces with Encoding Level of Detail. **Siggraph Asia** 2023.
- 16. Zixin Luo, Lei Zhou, Xuyang Bai, Hongkai Chen, Jiahui Zhang, **Yao Yao**, Shiwei Li, Tian Fang, Long Quan. ASLFeat: Learning Local Features of Accurate Shape and Localization. **CVPR** 2020. (>200 citations)
- 17. Lei Zhou, Zixin Luo, Tianwei Shen, Jiahui Zhang, Mingmin Zhen, **Yao Yao**, Tian Fang, Long Quan. Learning Temporal Camera Relocalization using Kalman Filtering. **CVPR** 2020. (Oral)

- 18. Tianwei Shen, Zixin Luo, Lei Zhou, **Yao Yao**, Shiwei Li, Jiahui Zhang, Tian Fang, Long Quan. Self-Supervised Learning of Depth and Motion Under Photometric Inconsistency. **ICCVW** 2019.
- 19. Zixin Luo, Tianwei Shen, Lei Zhou, Jiahui Zhang, **Yao Yao**, Shiwei Li, Tian Fang, Long Quan. Local Feature Augmentation with Cross-Modality Context. **CVPR** 2019. (Oral, >200 citations)
- 20. Shiwei Li, Zixin Luo, Mingmin Zhen, **Yao Yao**, Tianwei Shen, Tian Fang, Long Quan. Cross-atlas Convolution for Parameterization Invariant Learning on Textured Mesh Surface. **CVPR** 2019.
- 21. Zixin Luo, Tianwei Shen, Lei Zhou, Siyu Zhu, Runze Zhang, **Yao Yao**, Tian Fang, Long Quan. GeoDesc: Learning Local Descriptors by Integrating Geometry Constraints. **ECCV** 2018.
- 22. Shiwei Li, **Yao Yao**, Tian Fang, Long Quan. Reconstructing Thin Structures of Manifold Surfaces by Integrating Spatial Curves. **CVPR** 2018.

TEACHING

FOUNDINGS

| ILACIIIII | | | | | |
|--|---|---|---------------------|----------------------------|------|
| Teaching NJU IST Pattern Recognition | | Fall 2023 | | | |
| Teaching Assistant | | | | | |
| HKUST COMP5421 Computer Vision HKUST COMP2011 Introduction to Object-oriented Programming HKUST COMP5421 Computer Vision HKUST COMP2012 Object-Oriented Programming and Data Structures HKUST COMP2011 Introduction to Object-oriented Programming | | Spring 2019 Fall 2017 Spring 2017 Fall 2016 Spring 2016 | | | |
| | | | PROFESSIONAL SERV | VICES | |
| | | | Conference Reviewer | CVPR, ICCV, Neurips | 2023 |
| | | | | CVPR, Siggraph, ICRA, ECCV | 2022 |
| | | | | CVPR, ICLR | 2021 |
| CVPR, ECCV, Siggraph Asia, AAAI, BMVC | 2020 | | | | |
| CVPR, ICCV | 2019 | | | | |
| Journal Reviewer | TPAMI, TOG, ISPRS | 2023 | | | |
| | TPAMI, TOG, TCSVT | 2022 | | | |
| | TPAMI, TVCG, TOG | 2021 | | | |
| | TPAMI, IJCV, TIP, ISPRS IJCV, ISPRS | 2020 2019 | | | |
| | IJCV, ISI IGS | 2019 2015 | | | |
| AWARDS | | | | | |
| Honors | ICPR 2020 Best Student Paper Award (0.15%) | 2020 | | | |
| | Outstanding Undergraduate Thesis in NJU (2%) | 2015 | | | |
| | Outstanding Student in Jiangsu Province (0.5%) | 2014 | | | |
| | Outstanding Student in Nanjing University (5%) | 2014 | | | |
| Scholarships | HKUST Postgraduate Studentship | 2015 - 2018 | | | |
| | People's Scholarship | 2013 | | | |
| | National Scholarship (2%) | 2012 | | | |
| DOLLNIDINGG | | | | | |

Nanjing UniversityZijin Scholar Fund2023Nanjing UniversityStartup Fund2023NSF of ChinaExcellent Young Scholars Fund (Overseas)2022